<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A very mery and pleasaunt historie done not long since, in this realm of England written in Latine by Erasmus of Roterodame, dialoguewise, vnder the title of A coniuration or spirite ; newly translated into English, by Thomas Iohnson.</title>
            <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1567</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10510.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24458422</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24458422</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00394)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1851:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A very mery and pleasaunt historie done not long since, in this realm of England written in Latine by Erasmus of Roterodame, dialoguewise, vnder the title of A coniuration or spirite ; newly translated into English, by Thomas Iohnson.</title>
                  <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
                  <author>Johnson, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Bynneman, for William Pickring,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1567.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"From the colloquy Exorcismus"--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks all but four leaves of signature A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27694:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27694:1"/>
            <p>A very mery and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt Hiſtorie done not long ſince, in this realm of England. Written in Latine by Eraſmus of R<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terodame, Dialoguewiſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of a Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Spirite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newly tranſlated into Engliſh, <hi>by Thomas Iohnſon.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by Henrie Bynneman, for William Pickring. ANNO DOMINI. 1567.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="fragmentary_dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:27694:2"/>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27694:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>from the bridge the waye leadeth into the playne fielde.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>I remembre it well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>Of late a rumoure was ſpread among the huſbandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe quarters, that byſides this bridge ther walked a certaine Spirite,<note place="margin">Sprite.</note> whoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable howlings were ſundry tymes hearde:<note place="margin">Soule.</note> which they thought to be the ſoule of ſome man in thoſe places tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with moſt cruel puniſhments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>Who was the authour of this rumour?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>Who but <hi>Pole?</hi> and this was the preface of his Enterlude.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>What came in his mynde to fayne this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>I wot nere, but that ſuch is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature, deſirous to deceiue the fooliſh people, by ſuch ſort of delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. I will ſhew you what like pra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k he hath playd<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of late. We rode a good companie of vs togither to <hi>Richmond,</hi> wherof there were ſome, whome you would haue ſworne,<note place="margin">Richmond.</note> had ben both tall and ſtutdy fellows.<note place="margin">The i. Acte</note> The wether was
<pb facs="tcp:27694:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>very fayre, neither appered there any little clowde in the Skie. There <hi>Pole</hi> caſting his eyes vp towardes heauen: bleſſed all his face and ſhoulders with the ſigne of the Croſſe, and fayning in his countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as though he had ben afrayde, theſe words he ſpake to hym ſelfe: O immortall God, what doe I ſée? and beyng demaunded of thoſe that rode next vnto him what it was: Agayne, makyng a greater croſſe: O merciful God, I beſéech thée (quod he) take away from myne eyes this terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſight. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they deſirous to know what it was, moſte inſtantly required him to declare the viſion,<note place="margin">Viſion.</note> he caſtyng his eyes intentiuely vp agayn towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des heauen, and there with his fynger pointyng to one place: Sée you not yonder (quod he) an vgly Dragon,<note place="margin">A Dragon.</note> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with light burning hornes, and a winding taile? Which when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that they ſawe it: againe he had they ſhoulde beholde more earneſtly, ofte poyntyng with his finger alſo to the place, vntill at length an other of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27694:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the company, leſt he ſhould ſéeme that he could ſée but a little, ſayd alſo that be ſawe it. Lykewiſe did one or. ij. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for they were aſhamed not to ſée that which was ſo euident. But what néede many words? within. iij. dayes the rumour had perſuaded all Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that there appered ſuch a Monſter.<note place="margin">England.</note> A wonder it was howe the report of the people had augmented the fable,<note place="margin">Monſter.</note> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lacked there ſuch as wold in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt expound what this horrible ſight portended. Whoſe follie he much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced at, who was the Inuenter of the argument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>I know wel the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wit, but returne againe to the Spirite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>In the meanewhile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly, there reſorted vnto <hi>Pole,</hi> a certaine Prieſt named <hi>Fanne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fanne.</note> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not wel call in Latin <hi>Regulares,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Regulares,</note> Regulars, vnleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greke name agrée alſo, a pariſhe Prieſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the cure in one of the nexte Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. This ſame ſéemed vnto himſelfe not meanlie learned, and eſpecially in
<pb facs="tcp:27694:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>diuinitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>I perceyue it well, he was founde chiefe doer in the matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>About ſupper they fell in communication of this matter, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the ſpirite. When <hi>Pole</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that <hi>Fanne</hi> had not onely hearde of the rumour, but alſo beleued it to bée true, he beganne to intreate him, that bicauſe hée was a man both lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and godly, he woulde helpe that ſielly ſoule ſo cruelly tourmented. And if you doubte any thing (quod he) trie the matter: Walke aboute ten of the clocke at nyght to the bridge, and you ſhall heare terrible howlyngs. Take vnto you what companie you lyſte, ſo ſhall you heare more ſafely and ſurely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>What then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie</speaker>
               <p>After ſupper <hi>Pole</hi> as he was wont or accuſtomed, a haukyng or hunting, <hi>Fanne</hi> walkyng vp and down eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> darkneſſe had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away all ſure iudgement of thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, at lengthe heareth pitifull ſchrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:27694:2"/>fire out of their noſtrils, who aſſayde alſo to enter into the Circle, but that by waightie wordes he draue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with ſorrowe: At which <hi>Fanne</hi> taking heart of grace, the day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being wel appointed, commeth to the Circle, and prouoketh the Diuell to appere by many charms &amp; prayers.<note place="margin">Charmes.</note> And <hi>Pole</hi> with his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhewing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a far off, ſitting vpon black horſes, with terrible noyſes (as who ſhould ſay) they would faine haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Circle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>Had they no fire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>None at all, for that had chaunced vnto them not very well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: but here beginneth another tale. They brought with them a long rope which they dragged ſoftly on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, eche of them holding an ende in their handes, diſperſed themſelues abroade as thoughe they had bene ſo enforced by the vehemencie of <hi>Fanne</hi> his inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: and therwithall they tombled ouer and ouer both the Prieſtes &amp; alſo the Veſſell of holie Water which they
<pb facs="tcp:27694:1"/>had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>Had the pariſh Prieſt ſuch a rewarde for his good wil in furthering the matter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>Yea truely, yet had he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffer all this and more too, than to forſake the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded paſtime.<note place="margin">The. 3. Acte.</note> This done, when they came to talk togither <hi>Fan</hi> declareth vnto <hi>Pole</hi> in what dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger he was, and how ſtoutely he draue away both the Spirites with his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and that he had nowe taken ſuch an opinion, that there was not one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in Hell, were he neuer ſo hurtfull or bolde, which durſte or coulde come within the Circle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>That <hi>Fanne</hi> ſhould ſéeme truelie to be almoſt a foole.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Anthonie.</speaker>
               <p>Yet haue ye heard in effect nothing. The matter thus far procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in good time came <hi>Poles</hi> ſonne in lawe,<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Fanne his Sonne in lawe.</note> who had taken to wife his eldeſt daughter, a yong man (as you know) of a maruellous witte and pleaſaunte diſpoſition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>I know it wel, neither doth <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
